Welcome back. In the next few concepts,
お帰りなさい次のコンセプトでは
we will walk through critical steps for localizing
車両のローカライゼーションに非常に重要となるステップを
our car by implementing a particle filter.
粒子フィルターを実装しながら見ていきます
Our ultimate goal is determine how well each of
最終的な目的は粒子の位置で
our particle positions represents the actual position of our car.
実際の車両の位置をどれだけうまく表せるかを確認することです
To do this, we must use car sensor and map inputs to weigh each particle.
これを行うには 車両センサーと地図入力を使用して各粒子に重みづけする必要があります
In the next few concepts,
次のコンセプトでは
we will walk through this process for a single particle by
ひとつの粒子でこのプロセスを見ていきます
transforming car sensor landmark observations from the car coordinate system,
車両センサーのランドマーク観測を車両の座標系から
to the map coordinate system,
地図の座標系に変換し
associating these transformed observations with the nearest landmark on the map.
変換した観測を地図上の最も近いランドマークに関連付けます
Updating our particle weight by applying
それぞれの観測に多変数のガウス確率密度関数
the multivariate Gaussian probability density function for each measurement,
を適用して粒子の重みを更新します
then combining the probabilities of all the measurements by taking their product.
次に生成されたものの積をとって全観測の確率を結合します
This final weight is our posterior probability.
この最終の重みが事後確率です
In this video, we will go over the first step,
この動画では最初のステップとなる
transforming observations to map coordinates.
観測を地図座標に変換するステップを行います
This figure here depicts a car observing three nearby landmarks,
この図は車両が観測している車両近くの 3 つのランドマークを表しています
L5, L1, and L2.
L5 L1 と L2 です
The car sees them as observation one,
車両からは観測対象 1
observation two, and observation three.
観測対象 2 観測対象 3 が見えます
Remember that by convention,
慣例では 車両座標の
we define the car's coordinates such as X is
X は進行方向に対する向きを指し
pointed in the direction of the vehicle's heading with
Y は左に 90 度回転させた向き
y rotated plus 90 degrees or to the left perpendicular as depicted here.
を指しているのを覚えておいてください
The blue box in this figure represents a particle whose weight we want to update.
図の青色のボックスは粒子を表し これを更新していきます
To do this, we will transform the car observations to map coordinates.
更新をするため 車両の観測を地図座標に変換します
We can achieve this transformation by passing our data through
変換は 車両座標の位置付けを行う
a trigonometric function that maps car coordinates, to map coordinates.
三角関数を使ってデータを地図座標に渡します
This function is called a homogeneous transformation,
この関数は同次変換と呼ばれ
and is composed of a rotation in a translation.
平行移動における回転から成っています
Essentially, we all need to rotate the maps frame to match the particles point of view.
基本的には 地図の座標系を回転させて粒子の視点に合わせるだけです
Then we will move the origin of the frame to the location of the particle.
そのあと 元の枠を粒子の位置に移動します
We can do both of these steps in one matrix multiplication,
これらのステップは 1 つの行列の乗算で行うことができます
using the homogeneous transformation.
同次変換を使用します
We know that our particle has a heading of
粒子にはマイナス 90 度の方位と
negative 90 degrees and a map location of four come of five.
地図位置 (4,5) があります
We can visualize this process by drawing a coordinate frame at the map origin,
座標枠を描くとプロセスを視覚化できます
then determining the location of the particle frame in the map coordinate system.
次に 地図座標系で粒子枠の位置を確定します
To get to the particles frame from the mass point of view,
全体の視点から粒子の枠を得るには
we first have to rotate by negative 90 degrees like so,
マイナス 90 度に回転させてから
then we'll move to the particles position by
粒子の位置まで移動させます
passing our observation coordinates XC and YC,
観測座標 XC と YC
our particle coordinates XP and YP and a rotation angle theta of negative 90 degrees.
粒子座標 XP と YP 回転確度 θ のマイナス 90 度を渡します
This homogeneous transformation right here does exactly what we just did.
この同次変換で 今行った変換が行われます
This formulation with the extra one as a third row is known as homogeneous coordinates.
追加で 3 行目を持つこの定式化は同次座標と呼ばれます
More detail can be found in the instructor notes.
詳しくは講師注記をご覧ください
Let's quickly break down this homogeneous transformation here.
この同次変換を分解してみましょう
The two by two matrix in the top left represents the rotation component about the Z axis.
左上にある 2x2 行列は Z 軸に関する回転成分を表しています
Remember that we're only doing this in 2D right now.
今は 2 次元でのみ行っている点に注意してください
The third column here represents the translation component.
この 3 列目は転換成分を表しています
We complete the transformation by multiplying
変換を完了するため
through by the observation in car coordinates.
車両座標の観測にかけ合わせます
To summarize, this homogeneous transformation is a transformation
要約すると この同次変換は
from car coordinates to map coordinates in the maps frame.
地図枠内での車両座標から地図座標への変換になります
Using our observations in the car
車両座標系の観測と
coordinate system and our particle pose in the map system,
地図座標系の粒子の姿勢を用いると
we have everything we need to transform observations into map coordinates,
観測を地図座標に変換して 粒子の最終的な重み
and ultimately determine the final weight of our particle. Good luck.
を確定するために必要なすべてのものが揃います頑張ってください